SIMEON QUIRINUS

SMEELE

CONTACT INFO

E-mail simeonqs@hotmail.com

Phone Nr +49 179 4346618

Website simeonqs.github.io

LinkedIn linkedin.com/in/simeonqs

ABOUT ME

I'm an post doctoral researcher at Ecoscience, Aarhus University. I'm broadly interested in the evolution of complex cognition and culture, and more specifically in the emergence of socially learned vocal behaviours. I'm currently working on implementing a deep neural network to help monitor bat activity above Danish terrestrial and marine environment.

EDUCATION

Master of Biology

2016-2018

University of Southern Denmark | Odense, Denmark

- Courses in behavior, bio-acoustics, terrestrial ecology, statistics, research projects, Matlab, sound and hearing, marine mammals, biodiversity.
- Thesis topic: "Pinniped cognition: the ability to recall own behaviour on cue"

Bachelor of Biology (minor in Mathematics)

2013-2016

University of Southern Denmark | Odense, Denmark

- Courses in zoology, botany, ecology, ecotoxicology, statistics and mathematics.
- Thesis topic: "Spatial memory in Daubenton's bats"

EXPERIENCE

Post doctoral researcher

2019 - 2023

Wildlife Ecology, Ecoscience, Aarhus University | Aarhus, Denmark

- Passive acoustic monitoring of bats
- Supervisors: Morten Elmeros and Ole Roland Therkildsen

IMPRS doctoral researcher

2019 - 2023

Max Planck Institute of Animal Behavior and Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology | Radolfzell, Germany

- Parrot vocal and social complexity
- Supervisors: Dr. Mary Brooke McElreath and Dr. Lucy Aplin

Staff member 2022

Museum Haus Otto Dix | Hemmenhofen, Germany

 Helping visitors (in German) in the museum during weekends in the summer season

Research assistant 2019

University of Southern Denmark | Odense, Denmark

- Analysing large datasets on species demography and conservation
- Supervisor: Professor Dalia Amor Conde

Study group supervisor

2015-2017

University of Southern Denmark | Odense, Denmark

 Helping first year Natural Science students work in groups on biology and mathematics projects

Teaching assistant

2014-2015

University of Southern Denmark | Odense, Denmark

Teaching first year Natural Science students in the general biology course

VOLUNTEERING

Research assistant (internship)

2018 - 2019

University of Southern Denmark and Fuglezoo | Odense, Denmark

- Co-supervising master student working on cooperative and vocal behaviour in parakeets
- Supervisor: Professor Ole Næsby

Animal trainer 2017 - 2018

Marine Biological Research Centre | Kerteminde, Denmark

- Training grey seals, great cormorants and common murres
- Assisting with data collection for psychophysics, conservation and cognition
- Supervisor: Dr. Kirstin Anderson Hansen

Trainer and member general board

2014 - 2018

Odense SportsKlatreKlub (climbing gym) | Odense, Denmark

- Training the youth elite team, adult advanced team and schools
- Moving the club to new facilities and setting up the new management structure

Field assistant 2014

University of Southern Denmark | Odense, Denmark

- Collecting data from tit nest boxes
- Conducting observational study of great tit foraging behaviour
- Supervisor: Prof. Owen Jones

Biology field course

2021

Max Planck Institute of Animal Behavior | Radolfzell, Germany

 Gave a lecture on bio-acoustics and co-supervised a group of master students working on local dialects and aggression in great tits

General introduction biology

2014-2015

University of Southern Denmark | Odense, Denmark

- I worked as a teaching assistant during the biology part of a larger course that introduced natural science students to different subjects in the wider field
- I had the responsibility for groups of 20-30 students that worked on exercises and presented the solutions

ACHIEVEMENTS

Awards

- 2022 Small Cluster Grant CASCB (€ 10,000)
- 2021 Small Cluster Grant CASCB (€ 10,000)

ACTIVITIES

Peer reviews

- 2023 Methods in Ecology and Evolution
- 2022 PLOS Computational Biology
- 2022 Scientific Reports
- 2022 Ethology
- 2022 Ethology
- 2022 Scientific Reports
- 2021 Ecology and Evolution

Organisation

- 2021-current Preprint Team, Proceedings of the Royal Society
- 2021-2023 member Sustainability Group MPI-AB
- 2021 co-host Virtual ESLR Workshop (GatherTown)
- 2021 co-host Virtual IMPRS Grand Challenges Symposium (Zoom)
- 2020-2022 external PhD representative Max Planck Institute of Animal Behavior

PUBLICATIONS

2023

- preprint Smeele, S. Q., Senar J. C., Aplin, L. A. & McElreath, M. B. (2023). Evidence for vocal signatures and voice-prints in a wild parrot. BioRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2023.01.20.524864
- preprint Smeele, S. Q.*, Tyndel, S. A.*, Klump, B. C., Alarcon-Nieto, G. & Aplin, L. M. (2023). callsync: an R package for alignment and analysis of multi-microphone animal recordings. BioRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/ 2023.02.07.527470 [* co-first author]
- Mooney, A., Teare, J. A., Staerk, J., Smeele, S. Q., Rose, P., Edell, R. H., King, C. E., Conrad, L., & Buckley, Y. M. (2023). Flock size and structure influence reproductive success in four species of flamingo in 540 captive populations worldwide. Zoo Biology, 1–14. https://doi.org/10.1002/zoo.21753

2022

- Smeele, S. Q., Conde, D. A., Baudisch, A., Bruslund, S., Iwaniuk, A., Staerk, J., Wright, T. F., Young, A. M., McElreath, M. B. & Aplin, L. M. (2022). Coevolution of relative brain size and life expectancy in parrots. Proceedings of the Royal Society B, 289(1971), 20212397. https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2021.2397
- Smeele, S. Q. (2022). Using relative brain size as predictor variable: Serious pitfalls and solutions. Ecology and Evolution, 12, e9273. https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.9273
- preprint Smeele, S. Q.*, Tyndel, S. A.*, Aplin, L. A. & McElreath, M. B. (2022). Multi-level analysis of monk parakeet vocalisations shows emergent dialects between cities in the European invasive range. BioRxiv. https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.10.12.511863[*co-firstauthor]
- Bergler, C., Smeele, S.Q., Tyndel, S.A. et al. ANIMAL-SPOT enables animal-independent signal detection and classification using deep learning. Sci Rep 12, 21966 (2022). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-26429-y
- Torres Ortiz, S., **Smeele, S.Q.**, Champenois, J. & von Bayeren A. M. P. (2022). **Memory for own actions in parrots**. Sci Rep 12, 20561. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-25199-x

2021

Cantor, M.*, Chimento, M.*, Smeele, S. Q.*, He, P., Papageorgiou, D., Aplin, L.M., & Farine, D. R. (2021). Social network architecture and the tempo of cumulative cultural evolution. Proceedings of the Royal Society B, 288(1946), 20203107. https://doi.org/10.1098/rspb.2020.3107 [* co-first author]

2020

- Nielsen, R. O., da Silva, R., Juergens, J., Staerk, J., Sørensen, L. L., Jackson, J., Smeele, S. Q., & Conde, D. A. (2020). Standardized data to support conservation prioritization for sharks and batoids (Elasmobranchii). Data in brief, 33, 106337. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dib.2020.106337
- Bergler, C., Schmitt, M., Maier, A., Smeele, S., Barth, V., & Nöth, E. (2020, October). ORCA-CLEAN: A Deep Denoising Toolkit for Killer Whale Communication. In INTER-SPEECH (pp. 1136-1140). http://dx.doi.org/10.21437/Interspeech.2020-1316

2019

Smeele, S. Q., Anderson Hansen, K., Ortiz, S. T., Johansson, F., Kristensen, J. H., Larsson, J., Siebert, U. & Wahlberg, M. (2019). Memory for own behaviour in pinnipeds. Animal cognition, 22(6), 947-958. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10071-019-01286-x

CONFERENCES

Vocal Complexity and Social Learning Workshop

2023

Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Biology, Germany

Talk: 'Vocal flexibility in monk parakeets'

CES Hybrid Conference

2022

Aarhus University, Denmark

 Talk: 'Monk parakeets exhibit individual vocal signatures and populationlevel dialects in their vocalisations'

ASAB Easter Virtual Meeting

University of Bristol, UK

• Talk: 'Brainy lives: do larger brained parrots live longer?'

SKILLS

R, driving licence, GitHub, acoustic analysis

ATEX, Python, Bayesian statistics, teaching and supervision, international collaborations, field work

 \bullet \circ \circ Matlab, Bash, Git

Languages

English (fluent)

• Danish (fluent)

• Dutch (fluent)

• German (intermediate)

REFERENCES

Dr. Lucy M. Aplin

Affiliated Scientist Department of Migration

Max Planck Institute of Animal Behavior

+49 7732 1501-13 laplin@ab.mpg.de

Dr. Mary Brooke McElreath

Research Scientist

Department of Human Behavior, Ecology and Culture Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology +49 341 3550 330

mary_mcelreath@eva.mpg.de

Prof. Dalia. A. Conde

Associate Professor and Director of Science

Department of Biology and Conservation Science Alliance

University of Southern Denmark and Species 360

+45 60 18 59 78 dalia@biology.sdu.dk

PERSONAL

Date of Birth 02-08-1992

Place of Birth Assen, The Netherlands

Nationality Dutch

Location Aarhus, Denmark